<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Responsibly Sourced]]></title>
  <link href="http://DrewEaster.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://DrewEaster.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-08T11:47:12+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://DrewEaster.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrew Easter]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Twelve-factor config and Docker]]></title>
    <link href="http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2015/02/08/twelve-factor-config-and-docker/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-08T08:03:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2015/02/08/twelve-factor-config-and-docker</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Config confusion</h2>

<p>I recently wrote about what I see to be confusion over the way the <a href="http://www.12factor.net">Twelve-factor app</a> guidelines are interpreted with regard to app config. You can read that post <a href="http://www.dreweaster.com/blog/2015/01/21/a-confusing-side-to-Twelve-factor-app-configuration/">here</a>.</p>

<p>To summarise my argument, I think people tend to focus solely on the explicit guidelines in the <a href="http://12factor.net/config">Config</a> section, and overlook the additional advice &ndash; specific to config &ndash; given in the <a href="http://12factor.net/build-release-run">Build, release, run</a> section. The former simply speaks about reading app config from the environment, the latter clearly states that a software &lsquo;Release&rsquo; is a <em>uniquely versioned</em> combination of a &lsquo;Build&rsquo; <em>and</em> &lsquo;Config&rsquo;.</p>

<p>Suffice to say, I&rsquo;m quite surprised at the extent to which people manage to overlook the <a href="http://12factor.net/build-release-run">Build, release, run</a> section when discussing Twelve-factor config. It offers extremely specific advice with regard to managing <em>immutable</em> release packages, and I don&rsquo;t believe it&rsquo;s correct to claim you&rsquo;re doing Twelve-factor style config if you&rsquo;re not also following the <a href="http://12factor.net/build-release-run">Build, release, run</a> guidelines.</p>

<p>In this post, I want to address the implications of this view with regard to shipping applications in Docker containers. Once again, I see some conflict in what Twelve-factor has to say about config and  perceived best practices for Docker.</p>

<h2>The Docker way</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve digested a whole bunch of various opinions and best practices with regard to Docker, and a fairly consistent view is that containers should remain environment agnostic &ndash; i.e. the same container you generate at &lsquo;Build&rsquo; time should be deployable to <em>any</em> environment.</p>

<p>I get this, and I&rsquo;m in total agreement. There&rsquo;s certainly agreement here with Twelve-factor, at least in terms of what constitues a &lsquo;Build&rsquo;.  So, how would we supposedly do Twelve-factor config with this model? It appears to be quite simple as Docker lets us pass in environment variables when running a container, e.g.</p>

<p><code>docker run -e FOO=bar coolcompany/coolapp:1.0.0</code></p>

<p>This is saying, run <code>coolapp</code> with tag <code>1.0.0</code> passing in <code>bar</code> as the value for environment variable <code>FOO</code>. The Docker tag, in this fictitious example, is meant to represent the &lsquo;Build&rsquo; version of the app, and would have been generated during the build phase in the delivery pipeline.</p>

<p>This approach is absolutely consistent with the Twelve-factor <a href="http://12factor.net/config">Config</a> section &ndash; our application (encapsulated in the container) will read its configuration from the environment variable(s) provided. And, of course, we haven&rsquo;t tied the container image to a specific environment &ndash; this container looks very much like what Twelve-factor refers to as a &lsquo;Build&rsquo;.</p>

<p>Hold on, though. Whilst we&rsquo;ve satisfied the <a href="http://12factor.net/config">Config</a> section, we&rsquo;ve only partly satisfied the <a href="http://12factor.net/build-release-run">Build, release, run</a> section. In fact, I&rsquo;d go as far as saying that this is violating the <a href="http://12factor.net/build-release-run">Build, release, run</a> guidelines.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s take some quotes directly from the Twelve-factor guidelines:</p>

<blockquote><p>The release stage takes the build produced by the build stage and combines it with the deploy’s current config. The resulting release contains both the build and the config and is ready for immediate execution in the execution environment.</p></blockquote>

<p>and:</p>

<blockquote><p>Every release should always have a unique release ID, such as a timestamp of the release (such as 2011-04-06-20:32:17) or an incrementing number (such as v100). Releases are an append-only ledger and a release cannot be mutated once it is created. Any change must create a new release.</p></blockquote>

<p>In our example above, I think it&rsquo;s fair to say that this advice has been circumnavigated. We&rsquo;ve taken our &lsquo;Build&rsquo; and jumped straight to &lsquo;Run&rsquo;, altogether ignoring what Twelve-factor refers to as a &lsquo;Release&rsquo;. We&rsquo;ve <em>not</em> created a uniquely versioned, immutable release package and we&rsquo;ve burdened the &lsquo;Run&rsquo; phase with the additional responsibility of having to pass environment variables to the container. The &lsquo;Run&rsquo; phase has become more complicated than it should be.</p>

<p>This approach has maintained a distinct separation between code and config, whereas Twelve-factor very explicitly specifies that a &lsquo;Release&rsquo; <em>is</em> a combination of code and config. The Twelve-factor approach allows the &lsquo;Run&rsquo; phase to be dumb &ndash; it just launches whatever package you give it, needing no knowledge of application specific configuration. And, it naturally follows that rollbacks are a simple case of running the previously versioned release, with no need to worry about what the configuration for that version should be.</p>

<h2>An alternative approach</h2>

<p>This is where this post is bound to get murky and upset a few people. I&rsquo;m going to be heretical and suggest a model whereby we do create environment specific Docker containers. I can hear the cries of &ldquo;How very dare he?!&rdquo;</p>

<p>I propose the idea of taking our base &lsquo;Build&rsquo; image and creating a uniquely versioned &lsquo;Release&rsquo; image as a thin layer on top of it &ndash; oh the joys of image layering. This new image <em>does</em> embed the environment variables &ndash; specific to a chosen environment &ndash; within itself, rather than requiring they be passed to <code>docker run</code> on launch.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s look at an example Dockerfile to achieve this:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>FROM coolcompany/coolapp:1.0.0
</span><span class='line'>ENV FOO bar</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>We can then use this Dockerfile to build the &lsquo;Release&rsquo; image, giving it a unique version at the same time, e.g. <code>coolcompany/coolapp:1.0.0-staging-v11</code>.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve made up a convention here <code>{build_version}-{environment_name}-{release_number}</code> for tagging releases. Including the environment name in the tag might be a nice way of ensuring it&rsquo;s clear which environment the container is tied to.</p>

<p>So, our delivery pipeline continues to produce an environment agnostic container &lsquo;Build&rsquo; image, but, just at the point of deployment to our chosen environment, we create a new environment specific image and use this as our &lsquo;Release&rsquo;. Then, the &lsquo;Run&rsquo; phase need only be given the &lsquo;Release&rsquo; image version in order to execute the application.</p>

<p>This model sees &lsquo;Release&rsquo; packages created on demand &ndash; i.e. a &lsquo;Release&rsquo; package (Docker image) is create <em>just in time</em> at the point of deployment to a specified environment. From where environment variables are actually sourced and added to the Dockerfile, is beyond the realms of this post.</p>

<h2>The right way?</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve read enough so called best practices to expect this approach to anger some Docker/containerization purists. However, I genuinely see this as being a reasonable way to implement the Twelve-factor guidelines using Docker.</p>

<p>If not this approach, then what? For me, one reasonable way to challenge this model would be to challenge the whole Twelve-factor concept of <a href="http://12factor.net/build-release-run">Build, release, run</a>. If you disagree with the Twelve-factor concept of a &lsquo;Release&rsquo;, then by all means disagree with the content of this post!</p>

<p>Just like with my <a href="http://www.dreweaster.com/blog/2015/01/21/a-confusing-side-to-Twelve-factor-app-configuration/">related post</a> &ndash; and despite being sympathetic to the <a href="http://12factor.net/build-release-run">Build, release, run</a> advice &ndash; I&rsquo;m not necessarily arguing right or wrong here. It&rsquo;s just a case of pointing out what would constitute a pure implementation of the Twelve-factor guidelines on top of Docker.</p>

<p>Remember, the Twelve-factor guidelines were essentially invented by the Heroku gurus, and there are other PaaS technologies that also follow the same principles. It&rsquo;s just a specific way of tackling release management, and, whilst it may not be the <em>right</em> way of using Docker, I don&rsquo;t think it would be fair to say it&rsquo;s <em>wrong</em> either.</p>

<p>What do you think?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Customer experience makes the difference]]></title>
    <link href="http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2015/02/03/customer-experience-makes-the-difference/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-03T09:56:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2015/02/03/customer-experience-makes-the-difference</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this post, I&rsquo;m going to dip my toes into the world of customer experience (CX). This isn&rsquo;t a subject I&rsquo;ve written about before, but a recent sub-optimal hotel experience during a trip to Belgium has prompted this analysis.</p>

<p>Whilst this story does not relate specifically to technology, great customer experience is something that all businesses should pursue, whether technical or not in nature.</p>

<h2>Our story</h2>

<p>Back in early December, my wife and I booked a two night city break to Bruges (Belgium), to return for the third time to what will remain an unnamed hotel, a hotel that continued to rank amongst our top five hotels in the world. To beat those New Year blues, we&rsquo;d been looking to go away sooner, but delayed until the beginning of February due to the hotel having no availability for the entire month of January. With no specific explanation &ndash; within the online booking engine &ndash; for the complete lack of availability in January, it was natural to assume they were just fully booked.</p>

<p>A few days prior to our trip, my wife noticed on their website an explanation for the January blackout &ndash; turns out they were shutting the hotel for refurbishment. But, no worries, as the work would be over ready for our arrival.</p>

<p>On arrival at the hotel, it was immediately obvious that the work had not been completed &ndash; there were decorators inside and out, hammers banging, paint pots piled up in the hallways. During check-in, the desk staff made no reference to the refurbishment work that was going on around us, and we were eventually shown to our room.</p>

<p>To a backing track of relentless hammering outside the window, my wife asked our room escort about the Wellness Centre &ndash; the pool, jacuzzi, sauna etc. being one of the considerable advantages of this particular hotel. It was at this point that a member of staff finally acknowledged what was going on around us and this included breaking the news that the Wellness Centre was out of use. It turned out the refurbishment work had overrun (no s**t, Sherlock) and was expected to carry on for a further week.</p>

<p>Following a fairly short discussion, my wife and I concluded that we should move to a different hotel. Why?</p>

<h3>The hotel failed at every possible opportunity to acknowledge the problem</h3>

<p>The hotel had at least three clear opportunities to proactively acknowledge the problem:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong><em>At the point of booking</em></strong> &ndash; they could have at least warned of the potential risk of overrun</li>
<li><strong><em>In the days leading up to our arrival</em></strong> &ndash; a simple email would have been courteous</li>
<li><strong><em>On arrival</em></strong> &ndash; they could have immediately apologised at check-in and offered solutions</li>
</ul>


<p>The most damning thing is that we ultimately had to prise an apology out of the staff. If I&rsquo;d been managing the hotel, I&rsquo;d have personally welcomed every arriving guest, explained the issue and discussed ways to minimise the disappointment for them. It&rsquo;s a customer experience disaster that we were left to realise what was going on before the staff acknowledged it.</p>

<h3>The hotel had devised no proactive mitigation plan</h3>

<p>What&rsquo;s pretty clear is that the hotel staff, as a team, had failed to prepare for the fallout. Let&rsquo;s be honest, it&rsquo;s not difficult to predict that refurbishment works will overrun &ndash; not only should the hotel manager have prepared a mitigation plan, but that plan should have been communicated clearly to <em>every</em> member of staff.</p>

<p>They should have been ready for every single pre-booked guest arrival and had devised an individual, tailored mitigation solution for each one. This plan could have been communicated to the guest(s), at best, prior to arrival, and, at worst, immediately on arrival at the reception desk.</p>

<p>A great manager would have got every member of staff into a room, rallied the troops and ensured each team member was fully prepared to execute the mitigation plan. Unfortunately, the staff at our hotel seemed as bemused as we did, and this was extremely disappointing.</p>

<h2>What can be learned?</h2>

<p>So, given the clumsy nature of their handling of the situation, we checked ourselves out the hotel and found ourselves a room elsewhere (the first time we&rsquo;ve ever done that). The hotel that we&rsquo;d previously held so dear to our hearts, had undone years of customer loyalty development in a single day. As it turns out, we shouldn&rsquo;t have ignored the fact they&rsquo;d tumbled down the TripAdvisor rankings in the past few years &ndash; the warning signs were there.</p>

<p>Still, there&rsquo;s a good chance we&rsquo;d have forgiven them if they&rsquo;d demonstrated a desire to minimise our disappointment &ndash; we&rsquo;d probably have stayed where we were. Instead, not only are we unlikely to ever go back, but we&rsquo;re now unlikely to recommend anyone else to stay there either (and they&rsquo;ve had guests in the past directly off the back of our recommendations).</p>

<p>The lessons that can be learned from this experience are hardly original:</p>

<h3>A good product is worth little without great customer service</h3>

<p>The tangible product &ndash; ignoring the fact that some of it wasn&rsquo;t available at the time &ndash; was seemingly unchanged. This is still a fabulous looking boutique hotel, in a fabulous location. The rooms are beautiful and the breakfasts fantastic. But, that just isn&rsquo;t enough without delightful customer service to go along with it.</p>

<p>Never ever ever think your tangible product will make up for lapses in customer service. There&rsquo;s no difference between product and service &ndash; your product <em>includes</em> the service.</p>

<h3>Don&rsquo;t rest on your laurels</h3>

<p>You can&rsquo;t rely on your customers&#8217; loyalty through past experience. Just because you&rsquo;ve won their loyalty in the past, it doesn&rsquo;t mean you can screw up in the present. Loyalty is a pretty fickle concept and, if you mess with your customers, they&rsquo;ll look elsewhere for a better all round experience.</p>

<h3>Customer service is the most important differentiator</h3>

<p>As a market becomes more and more competitive, the opportunities to differentiate on your tangible product are reduced &ndash; it&rsquo;s not always easy to create a truly original product. So, whilst your competitors continue to iterate blindly on their tangible product, spread your resources to accommodate improving all round customer experience. Service your customers in delightful ways, and they&rsquo;ll keep on coming back to you for more. Do not underestimate your ability to differentiate yourself through great service.</p>

<h2>Make the difference</h2>

<p>As stated at the beginning of this post, customer experience is important for <em>every</em> business &ndash; little or large, technical or non-technical.</p>

<p>Great customer experience makes the difference, so make it your difference.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A confusing side to twelve factor app configuration]]></title>
    <link href="http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2015/01/21/a-confusing-side-to-twelve-factor-app-configuration/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-21T18:39:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2015/01/21/a-confusing-side-to-twelve-factor-app-configuration</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m sure I&rsquo;m not the only one who breathed a sign of relief when the clever brains behind Heroku published the <a href="http://12factor.net">Twelve Factor App</a> guidelines. Here was a reliable set of principles &ndash; born out of real life experience &ndash; that immediately hit home, providing sensible advice for overcoming the many pitfalls developers and operations teams have fought relentless battles with time and time again.</p>

<p>One of the principles that I was especially able to connect with is the advice regarding from where applications should read their <a href="http://12factor.net/config">configuration</a>. Having regularly encountered config file hell over the years, this simple, platform agnostic approach to supplying config to an application makes a whole lot of sense. There have, though, been some misunderstandings with regard to this advice, <a href="http://blog.doismellburning.co.uk/2014/10/06/twelve-factor-config-misunderstandings-and-advice/">and this blog post</a> by Kristian Glass does a good job of highlighting one such misunderstanding &ndash; Twelve Factor does not dictate from where the environment should be populated, only that an app should read from it.</p>

<p>So, with a major misunderstanding out the way, we are left with a whole bunch of options as to how we populate the environment. Outside of the extreme abstraction of a PaaS environment like Heroku, something like Consul &ndash; the distributed key/value store &ndash; is one such solution. And in this <a href="https://hashicorp.com/blog/twelve-factor-consul.html">blog post</a> by <a href="https://hashicorp.com">Hashicorp</a>, that very solution is covered quite nicely.</p>

<p>But, hang on, has something been overlooked?</p>

<p>I&rsquo;d like to challenge Hashicorp&rsquo;s claim that this approach is compatible with Twelve Factor principles. My personal opinion &ndash; on which I&rsquo;m very happy to be challenged &ndash; is that there is a further critical piece of advice, regarding configuration, contained within the Twelve Factor guidelines &ndash; you just have to turn to a different page.</p>

<p>This additional piece of advice is contained with the section titled <a href="http://12factor.net/build-release-run">Build-Release-Run</a>. As far as I&rsquo;m concerned, the advice here is pretty crystal clear &ndash; a &lsquo;Release&rsquo; is a combination of a &lsquo;Build&rsquo; <em>and</em> &lsquo;Config&rsquo;. This <em>immutable</em> artifact is uniquely versioned and is deployed and rolled back as an atomic unit. This is how Heroku does it, and the open source <a href="http://www.docker.com">Docker</a> based PaaS <a href="http://www.deis.io">Deis</a> has the <a href="http://docs.deis.io/en/latest/reference/terms/release/#release">same approach</a>. I&rsquo;m leaving out other PaaS tech that also follows this model.</p>

<p>It would be hard to deny that this approach makes deployments very easy to reason about. By bundling together code alongside environment specific config, you simplify release management and tracking. For example, if you need to rollback, you don&rsquo;t have to manage that as two separate actions &ndash; it&rsquo;s an atomic action and will return you to the last known uniquely versioned, operationally sound combination of code and config.</p>

<p>So, whilst it&rsquo;s true that Twelve Factor does not dictate from <em>where</em> the environment should be populated, it&rsquo;s pretty clear that it does say <em>when</em> it should be. The source of environment configuration should be read <strong><em>when preparing a release</em></strong>, and that any change to config, just like with a change to code, <strong><em>results in a new release</em></strong>.</p>

<p>Therefore, any approach to managing configuration, in a similar way to Hashicorp&rsquo;s advice, would not appear to be compatible with the Twelve Factor guidelines. They are promoting a model where the &lsquo;Build&rsquo; and &lsquo;Config&rsquo; are not atomically bundled as a &lsquo;Release&rsquo; and, as such, this model is violating a fundamental Twelve Factor principle &ndash; if your code and config is managed in separate lifecycles, it ain&rsquo;t Twelve Factor compatible.</p>

<p>One could quite easily challenge the &lsquo;Build + Config = Release&rsquo; advice:</p>

<ol>
<li>It doesn&rsquo;t appear to leave any room for runtime config changes</li>
<li>It&rsquo;s not completely clear how it would work with dynamic service discovery</li>
</ol>


<p>Sometimes, however, the advantages of predictable, easy to reason about deployments outweigh the benefits of such niceties</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not debating here what&rsquo;s the right or wrong way, I&rsquo;m just pointing out that the Twelve Factor advice is very clear about the meaning of a &lsquo;Release&rsquo;, and, therefore, any method that circumvents this, cannot claim to be compatible with the guidelines.</p>

<p>Just saying.</p>

<h3>UPDATE 2015-01-21 20:10</h3>

<p>Spring are also claiming that the <a href="http://projects.spring.io/spring-cloud/spring-cloud.html">Spring Cloud</a> approach to configuration is Twelve Factor compatible in this <a href="http://spring.io/blog/2015/01/13/configuring-it-all-out-or-12-factor-app-style-configuration-with-spring?utm_content=bufferfa5a5&amp;utm_medium=social&amp;utm_source=twitter.com&amp;utm_campaign=buffer">blog post</a>. I think this is making the same mistake as Hashicorp. If configuration is able to change independently from a release &ndash; as is described in this post &ndash; then it&rsquo;s not in the spirit of the Twelve Factor App.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lessons from my first startup failure]]></title>
    <link href="http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2014/10/02/lessons-from-my-first-startup-failure/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-02T15:13:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2014/10/02/lessons-from-my-first-startup-failure</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s been a while since I last posted here, and good reason &ndash; I&rsquo;ve been trying to run a startup! As this is a technically focused blog &ndash; and given my startup experiences were mainly commercially focused &ndash; I didn&rsquo;t have all that much to say here. But, now I&rsquo;ve experienced my first startup failure, I thought I&rsquo;d write about it here (even though it&rsquo;s not really technical content).</p>

<p>It has become somewhat customary for entrepreneurs to write about the good times and the bad. In either case &ndash; often even more relevant in the case of the bad times &ndash; it seems quite useful to share with others the lessons one learnt along the way. So, this is me sharing some of the lessons I learnt during my first startup failure experience. Let&rsquo;s get on with it.</p>

<h2>Be wary of complex dependencies</h2>

<p>If your business model is reliant on others (partners) investing in changes to their own technology systems, your chances of success are considerably lowered.</p>

<p>All startups have an implicit dependency on customers buying their product/service. Any additional dependencies just hugely complicate things. Try to keep as much within your own control as possible.</p>

<h2>Take good feedback with a pinch of salt</h2>

<p>Most people will tell you how great your idea is &ndash; it&rsquo;s human nature. The only way to be sure you&rsquo;ve got a good product is by getting someone to actually pay you. Until someone actually hands over money for your product/service, you haven&rsquo;t validated the problem you are solving (this is skewed somewhat towards B2B software).</p>

<h2>Identifying a problem is not enough</h2>

<p>Whilst clearly important, it&rsquo;s not enough to just identify a problem. Yes, your business may well solve a real pain point in theory, but it still doesn&rsquo;t mean you can actually execute on it successfully. Commercial complexities (e.g. a deeply tangled industry) can still make even a good idea impossible to actually execute on, especially for a startup.</p>

<h2>Be patient before diving in</h2>

<p>Even if you can afford to, it might not be a good idea to quit your job until you&rsquo;ve found something you are really passionate about building/solving. Identify a problem you&rsquo;ve had in your own life/job, don&rsquo;t try to force ideas out of nothing &ndash; it&rsquo;s contrived. You have to be patient and let the idea come to you &ndash; if that means working for others until you do, then so be it.</p>

<p>Make the most of working for larger companies where you can network with those in business areas you are not familiar with. The gaps will be there, you just need to put yourself in the position to see them.</p>

<h2>It&rsquo;s much harder than you could possibly imagine</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s going to be infinitely more difficult to succeed than you think. Success is a combination of a good idea, impeccable execution, luck, who you know etc.</p>

<p>There is a myth doing the rounds that it&rsquo;s easier than ever to start a startup. In reality it&rsquo;s just a cultural mind shift, the actual chances of succeeding are just as low as they have ever been. The &lsquo;anyone can build an app&rsquo; delusion is really unhelpful.</p>

<p>And, it will take five times longer to succeed than you probably think it will. Most successful startups have been operating a lot longer than you think they have &ndash; you&rsquo;re facing many years of blood, sweat and tears (and you still might fail).</p>

<p>Also, be willing to acknowledge, therefore, that the idea of running your own business might look much better on paper than it does in reality.</p>

<h2>A tech startup is not just about tech</h2>

<p>Marketing and sales will most likely be 80% of the effort in a startup&rsquo;s success story. Don&rsquo;t be under any illusions &ndash; a good product won&rsquo;t sell itself. A warning for you techies out there &ndash; don&rsquo;t be fooled into thinking that you only need tech skills to get a business off the ground. It&rsquo;s not true, seriously!</p>

<p>Accordingly, non-techie entrepreneurs shouldn&rsquo;t feel disadvantaged that they don&rsquo;t have tech skills. This is not to say that tech isn&rsquo;t hugely important (I obviously think it is), but it&rsquo;s not a one-way ticket to success.</p>

<h2>Recognise when the game is up</h2>

<p>Be prepared to recognise when it&rsquo;s time to call it a day. Cut through the false positives in order to make an objective assessment of your business. There&rsquo;s a fine line between sensible persistence and blind optimism. It&rsquo;s not always advisable to keep the faith if every indicator of business healthiness is against you. Maybe it&rsquo;s just not a good idea, or maybe the market is just not ready, for any number of commercial reasons, to accommodate your product.</p>

<h2>Don&rsquo;t do it for money</h2>

<p>Don&rsquo;t bother doing it if you are doing so in any way for money. Be totally honest with yourself from the outset. Unless your only reason for starting a business is to build a great product/service then don&rsquo;t bother. For most people, it they are truly honest, the idea of becoming rich is the real motivator deep down.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What a storming idea]]></title>
    <link href="http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2013/12/07/what-a-storming-idea/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-07T09:46:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2013/12/07/what-a-storming-idea</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Firstly, an important disclosure &ndash; having only just stumbled across the practice of <a href="http://ziobrando.blogspot.be/2013/11/introducing-event-storming.html">Event Storming</a>, I’ve not yet had the opportunity to experiment with it myself. However, sometimes a concept/practice makes such immediate sense in one’s mind, that one feels compelled to talk about it!</p>

<p>This post feels like quite a natural successor to my previous post on <a href="http://www.dreweaster.com/blog/2013/12/02/event-driven-architecture-ftw/">Event-driven Architecture</a>. In that post, I discussed some of the tangible benefits of EDA, and this follow up introduces the practice of <a href="http://ziobrando.blogspot.be/2013/11/introducing-event-storming.html">Event Storming</a>, a fledgling Domain Driven Design influenced practice that goes hand in hand with EDA to assist product teams in exploring the complexity of their business domain.</p>

<p>It’s not my intention to write a long article on Event Storming &ndash; I encourage you to read Alberto Brandolini’s  <a href="http://ziobrando.blogspot.be/2013/11/introducing-event-storming.html">introduction</a> instead &ndash; but I want to share my biggest takeaways from this new learning.</p>

<h2>The Domain-Relational Impedance Mismatch</h2>

<p>In my experience of domain modelling, the biggest mistake I’ve seen made, time and time again, is to fail to involve the most important people ‘in the room’. The reason for this is that far too many projects take a <em>persistence oriented</em> approach to modelling, as opposed to a <em>business oriented</em> approach. Put simply, by tending to address model genesis using only technical team members, teams get sucked into allowing technical persistence concerns to shape their modelling approach. It’s not unusual for domain experts to be involved only at the user interface level, leaving software engineers and DBAs to make decisions that they are probably the least qualified to be making. The ultimate success of a software project resides on how well domain complexity has been tackled, and so it seems crazy for domain experts to be absent from the modelling process.</p>

<p>Let’s be absolutely clear &ndash; a domain model exists in spite of persistence technology, not because of it. A model is not a technical concept; it is a reflection of a business domain that exists in real-life, not inside a machine.</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;A domain model exists in spite of persistence technology, not because of it.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>Whilst NoSQL technology is becoming more popular, it’s still fairly normal to see domain modelling tackled using entity relationship (ER) diagrams &ndash; something quite familiar to engineers and DBAs. That wily old fox, the relational model, is still recognised by many as the de facto way to practice domain modelling. However, Domain Driven Design (DDD) teaches us a much better way, and does not make room for persistence concerns in our conversations &ndash; models spawned using DDD practices typically appear very different to what they’d look like had ER modelling been applied instead.</p>

<p>You’re probably familiar with the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Object-relational_impedance_mismatch">object-relational impedance mismatch</a> concept, but I think our problems extend much further than that; I believe DDD teaches us of a domain-relational impedance mismatch. That is, the relational model is not a natural fit for addressing domain model complexity, and thus should not be trusted to do so.</p>

<h2>The light at the end of the tunnel</h2>

<p>So, we know we&rsquo;re doing it wrong, but how do we then ensure we get both the right people in the room (domain experts), and a method to support effective communication of domain complexity? This is where I believe we should look to Event Storming to help us out.</p>

<p>From my initial learnings on Event Storming, I can wholeheartedly say that this technique appears to offer a very attractive way to ensure focus remains on the business rather than technical implementation. It forces the right people &ndash; domain experts &ndash; to be in the room, thus ensuring core business flows are identified, bounded contexts are defined and consistency boundaries are clarified.</p>

<p>Event Storming does infer an event-driven architecture (EDA), but I hope my <a href="http://www.dreweaster.com/blog/2013/12/02/event-driven-architecture-ftw/">previous post</a> serves to address why you should be doing that anyway. It finally gives us an accessible technique that allows domain experts and technical specialists to work together to tackle domain complexity effectively. It’s a really exciting prospect and I look forward to applying it both in existing and future projects.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Silicon Valley Mindset]]></title>
    <link href="http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2013/12/04/the-silicon-valley-mindset/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-04T22:01:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2013/12/04/the-silicon-valley-mindset</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I&rsquo;m currently on a temporary work assignment in San Jose, I recently wrote an article for <a href="http://thecroydoncitizen.com/">The Croydon Citizen</a> about my experiences in Silicon Valley. It&rsquo;s great to have become part of the <a href="http://croydontechcity.com/">Croydon Tech City</a> movement, and so it was nice to contribute an article in support of the great work being done to promote Croydon as a new hub for tech startups in the UK.</p>

<p>Check out my article here:</p>

<p><a href="http://thecroydoncitizen.com/croydon-tech-city/silicon-valley-mindset/">http://thecroydoncitizen.com/croydon-tech-city/silicon-valley-mindset/</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Event-driven Architecture FTW]]></title>
    <link href="http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2013/12/02/event-driven-architecture-ftw/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-02T21:41:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2013/12/02/event-driven-architecture-ftw</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>A quick primer on EDA</h2>

<p>First of all, let&rsquo;s delegate to the all-knowing source, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Event-driven_architecture">Wikipedia</a>, to give us a concise definition of Event-driven architecture (EDA):</p>

<blockquote><p>&ldquo;Event-driven architecture (EDA) is a software architecture pattern promoting the production, detection, consumption of, and reaction to events.&rdquo;</p></blockquote>

<p>It&rsquo;s pretty unusual to encounter a software engineer who hasn&rsquo;t dabbled with publish-subscribe semantics &ndash; or anything resembling the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Observer_pattern">Observer Pattern</a> &ndash; at some point in their engineering adventures. It&rsquo;s hard to ignore, when faced with a challenge to simplify some programming problem, the draw of decoupling a producer of something from one or many consumers of that something. Not only does it divide responsibility (making code easier to test for starters), it also clears the way for an asynchronous programming model in use cases where producers needn&rsquo;t be blocked by the actions of an interested consumer.</p>

<p>If you can appreciate the power of publish-subscribe, you&rsquo;re unlikely to have much trouble in figuring out how Event-driven architecture (EDA) could help you. It only requires a small leap of faith to realise that pattern you used to solve that micro problem, in some isolated component within your system, can become a macro pattern to underpin a system-wide architectural style.</p>

<p>So, let us return to that Wikipedia definition. I think we could reasonably interpret that definition to understand EDA as the art of designing a system around the principle of using events &ndash; concise descriptions of state changes or significant occurrences in the system &ndash; to drive behaviour both within and between the applications that make up an entire platform.</p>

<h3>Production</h3>

<p>Production of an event involves some application component/object generating a representation of something that has happened &ndash; maybe a state change to an entity, or maybe the occurrence of some activity (e.g. a user viewed page X). Rather than notifying specific consumers, the producer will simply pass the event to some infrastructural component that will deal with ensuring the event can be consumed by anything that&rsquo;s interested in it.</p>

<h3>Detection</h3>

<p>It&rsquo;s my belief that the Wikipedia definition is essentially referring to the mechanism that sits between a producer and consumer (the infrastructure piece) &ndash; the logic that ensures events are passed to interested consumers.</p>

<h3>Consumption</h3>

<p>Consumption is the act of an interested consumer receiving an event for which it is interested in. This is still most likely a part of the infrastructure piece (e.g. a message bus). There might be a whole bunch of stuff here about reliable delivery, failure recovery etc.</p>

<h3>Reaction</h3>

<p>Reaction is the fun part where a consumer actually performs some action in response to the event that it has consumed. For example, imagine you register a user on your website and you want to send them a welcome email. Rather than bundling the responsibility for sending email within your domain model, just create a consumer to listen into a UserRegisteredEvent and send an email from there. This nicely decouples the email delivery phase and also allows it to be done asynchronously &ndash; you probably don&rsquo;t need, or want, email delivery to be a synchronous action. Also, imagine you have further requirements relating to post registration behaviour &ndash; your domain model would soon become unwieldy with all that extra responsibility. Not one to want to violate the Single Responsibility Principle (SRP), you sensibly use event-driven programming to separate all those actions into separate consumers, allowing each behaviour to be tested in isolation, and retain simplicity in your domain model.</p>

<h2>Events everywhere</h2>

<p>As previously alluded to, it&rsquo;s far from unusual to see fragments of event-driven programming in many applications. However, it&rsquo;s another step entirely to see event-driven programming adopted in such a way that it becomes an endemic architectural pattern &ndash; that is, where an entire platform uses events to underpin all its moving parts. To be successful with EDA, it needs to become a fundamental mindset that drives all design decisions, rather than just a pattern that used in some isolated parts of a wider system.</p>

<p>I want to evaluate a series of application/platform features that, whilst may sit outside of core business workflows, fit really nicely with EDA. This should help to realise why EDA can be a very fruitful path to follow.</p>

<h3>WebHooks (the Evented Web)</h3>

<p>WebHooks is a fairly high level concept that encompasses the use of HTTP as a form of publish-subscribe mechanism. Whilst there are more recent attempts to create more standards around this &ndash; <a href="http://progrium.com/blog/2012/11/19/from-webhooks-to-the-evented-web/">calling it the Evented Web</a> &ndash; the fundamental idea is to allow a consumer to register a callback URL with some remote resource (using HTTP) that will be invoked by the hosting service whenever some event occurs relating to that resource. A really well known example is post-commit hooks on Github &ndash; any external tool (e.g. a CI server, a bug tracker) can register interest in commits to a repository and react in whatever way that makes sense in their context.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m pretty convinced that the Evented Web paradigm has got a lot of growth potential and will become a de facto expectation of any well designed service API. What should be clear is how easy it would be to add WebHooks functionality to your own application if you are already applying EDA across the board.</p>

<h3>Big Data</h3>

<p>I do kind of detest using the term &lsquo;Big Data&rsquo; as it&rsquo;s uncomfortably ambiguous and vague. However, for the purposes of this article, I&rsquo;m going to stick with it (strike me down). If, for now, we think of Big Data as a way of capturing shed loads of data to enable business intelligence, we should be able to see quickly that events occurring within an application might be a great source of all that lovely data. If you&rsquo;ve adopted EDA, your Big Data pipeline may just be a consumer of all your application events. You might dump all those events into HDFS for future batch processing, and, given you are essentially subscribing to a real-time event feed, you might also drive your real-time analytics use cases as well.</p>

<h3>Monitoring</h3>

<p>Unless you are someone who really couldn&rsquo;t give a damn, you&rsquo;re going to want some monitoring tools in place to give a thorough insight into the health of your system in production. Common monitoring solutions may include, amongst other things, a bunch of smart dashboards full of sexy graphs, and some threshold alerting tools to help spot potential problems as soon as an incident starts. Either way, both these tools are driven by time series data that represents &lsquo;stuff&rsquo; happening within an application. What better way to capture this &lsquo;stuff&rsquo; than sucking events in from your event streams? Again, if you&rsquo;ve already followed EDA, you&rsquo;re going to get some pretty quick monitoring wins.</p>

<h3>Log file analysis</h3>

<p>There is possibly some crossover here with monitoring, and even Big Data, but I think it deserves its own special mention. If you imagine logs as comprehensive streams of events, assuming you&rsquo;ve followed an EDA style, you can pretty much get log analysis for free. Just suck your logs into some analysis tools (e.g. <a href="http://logstash.net/">Logstash</a> and <a href="http://www.elasticsearch.org/overview/kibana/">Kibana</a>), and you&rsquo;re pretty much good to go. Just remember that it&rsquo;s perfectly reasonable to use events to represent errors too (which could contain any relevant stack trace).</p>

<h3>Test-driven development (TDD)</h3>

<p>Okay, so TDD is not an application feature, it&rsquo;s part of the engineering process. However, if our architecture decisions can help to improve our quality process, then that can&rsquo;t be a bad thing. Event-driven programming encourages a code level design approach that follows the <a href="http://pragprog.com/articles/tell-dont-ask">Tell, Don&rsquo;t Ask</a> pattern. You tell an object to do something, which leads to an event, or events, being published. So, what&rsquo;s this got to do with TDD? In my experience, it&rsquo;s much easier to reason about your code, and define more coherent specifications, if your testing style mimics &lsquo;given this input (command), I expect this event, or events, to be produced&rsquo;. A test first approach is very compatible with this style, and makes you think in a much more behavioural (think BDD) way.</p>

<h2>For the win</h2>

<p>Right, we&rsquo;ve covered a primer of EDA and seen how it can be used to drive both core business flows, cross cutting concerns, and even our quality process. I believe this knowledge makes a very compelling case for adoption of EDA &ndash; why would you bake in custom solutions for capturing Big Data, doing health check monitoring etc, when you can simply piggy back these features off of your core architecture? Hopefully, you wouldn&rsquo;t! All sorts of wonderful acronyms pop into my head at this point &ndash; KISS, DRY, SRP etc. And don&rsquo;t we all love acronyms?</p>

<p>But can we go even further?</p>

<h2>Going the whole hog with event sourcing</h2>

<p>This discussion leads so elegantly into the final part of this blog post &ndash; event sourcing. Event sourcing is an approach to persistence that means the state of an entity &ndash; more specifically, an Aggregate Root in DDD speak &ndash; is made up of all the events, representing state changes, it has emitted over time. So, rather than store current state in a database, you simply load the historical sequence of events (from an event store) and apply them in order to obtain current state. I will leave it up to the reader to pursue the full benefits of using event sourcing, but here are some of the headline wins:</p>

<ul>
<li>Supports a simple, and very scalable approach to persistence. An event store can be as simple as an append only log file.</li>
<li>Gives you a full history of every state change and that&rsquo;s great for producing an audit log (something you might want anyway, even without event sourcing).</li>
<li>Can still utilise snapshots of current state for performance optimisation when replaying.</li>
<li>Very compatible with a test first, behavioural approach to testing.</li>
<li>Plays very nice with the <a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/CQRS.html">CQRS</a> architectural pattern, a very practical way to bake scalability into your applications by maintaining separate paths for reads and writes.</li>
</ul>


<p>If you&rsquo;re going to go down the EDA route, why limit just your applications to an event-driven style? If it&rsquo;s possible to maintain state via the events you&rsquo;re already publishing, why maintain a separate database at all? Storing events for all time might seem like a storage burden but, seriously, are we still worrying about the cost of storage in 2013? Storing current state in a database is a &lsquo;lossy&rsquo; approach &ndash; once you&rsquo;ve overwritten existing state, you can never get it back. Martin Thompson summed all this up so concisely in a recent tweet:</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" lang="en"><p><a href="https://twitter.com/ashic">@ashic</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hintjens">@hintjens</a> I like, &quot;A database is a cache of the event log&quot;.</p>&mdash; Martin Thompson (@mjpt777) <a href="https://twitter.com/mjpt777/statuses/407534444803661824">December 2, 2013</a></blockquote>


<script async src="http://DrewEaster.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>There are way too many compelling reasons for wanting to keep a history of everything and it&rsquo;s impossible to avoid being courted by that proposition.</p>

<p>I think this is a really fascinating area of exploration &ndash; sometimes traditional CRUD might be a better choice, but the more I work with event sourcing, and the more comfortable I feel with EDA in general, the harder it becomes to find good reasons against following this path.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>So that wraps up a fairly lengthy discussion on EDA and how an event-driven mindset can promote a coherent strategy for the way you build software. One of the toughest things we face as software engineers is maintaining a consistency in style, especially in large teams. My ideal vision is for code to speak the architecture patterns on which it is crafted, such that no engineer could ever doubt what is expected of them when refactoring or adding new features. For me, EDA is an enabler of this vision, and will help to bridge the gap between doing the right thing (building product features your users love), and doing the thing right (consistent and elegant technical solutions).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The fallacy of the omniscient domain model]]></title>
    <link href="http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2013/11/17/the-fallacy-of-the-omniscient-domain-model/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-17T17:20:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2013/11/17/the-fallacy-of-the-omniscient-domain-model</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Complexity. As software engineers, it&rsquo;s pretty hard to make it beyond lunch without someone mentioning it. But, what is it exactly? Most of us probably think we sussed this out a long time ago &ndash; hell, we&rsquo;re probably preaching the KISS and DRY principles on a daily basis. However, complexity in software is a multi-faceted beast and, with that in mind, taking the time to reflect on your own view of complexity, you may reveal a bunch of defective preconceptions.</p>

<p>One of these preconceptions, one which I&rsquo;ve failed to question effectively myself in the past, is that a &lsquo;simple&rsquo; domain model is one that can encompass the entire domain of an enterprise. The other preconception is that &lsquo;simple&rsquo; architecture means few moving parts.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s address each one individually.</p>

<p>Imagine a completely DRY, one-size-fits-all domain model that manages to perfectly model the domain of an entire enterprise. This model is infinitely malleable and able to accommodate future changes without adversely affecting existing code dependant on it. Are you struggling to imagine this? I hope so, because I don&rsquo;t think it&rsquo;s possible in anything other than the most basic of business domains. Regardless, this a very common approach and, instead of being simple, it adds an alarming amount of overall complexity. Ultimately, the intertwining of vaguely related entities makes it impossible to make changes in one place without having to untangle deep dependencies elsewhere.</p>

<p>If, instead, you apply some of the core principles of Domain Driven Design (Domains, Subdomains, Bounded Contexts) to any enterprise, it&rsquo;s natural to materialise multiple models that exist within the different subdomains and contexts that make up the wider domain. This approach, which actually reflects the structure of the real business, reduces overall complexity &ndash; dependencies are untangled by design, making changes more achievable in isolation.</p>

<p>One important thing to note here &ndash; you&rsquo;re not necessarily violating the DRY principle if an entity appears in multiple contexts. Maybe you&rsquo;ve just failed to successfully tweak the Ubiquitous Language for each context, such that you&rsquo;re recognising that entity to mean different things in those different contexts.</p>

<p>So, now onto our second preconception &ndash; does simple architecture mean few moving parts? My previous argument may seem overly convenient given it implicitly provides support to my next case &ndash; it&rsquo;s most likely true that the introduction of multiple bounded contexts and/or subdomains will lead to more moving parts. But does that actually equate to complexity?</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve all seen over-engineered software that throws in a message queue here, another message queue over there, neither appearing to offer any discernible value. I&rsquo;m certainly not advocating that! But these over imaginative solutions shouldn&rsquo;t be confused with DDD influenced design decisions to separate contexts and integrate them effectively where necessary.</p>

<p>Applying the KISS principle to architecture doesn&rsquo;t necessarily mean a system with fewer moving parts. A simple system is one that is highly adaptable and reactive to business changes &ndash; thus, the number of moving parts alone can&rsquo;t be considered a good measure of complexity.</p>

<p>I hope the arguments I&rsquo;ve made in this article help to address some common misconceptions. I do believe the concept of a simple, single, all-knowing domain model is a fallacy. Feel confident to apply DDD principles, be proud of your separate cohesive models, and don&rsquo;t fear the additional moving parts you might adopt in the process.</p>

<p>Complexity is not always what it seems.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Akka, DDD, CQRS, Event Sourcing and Me]]></title>
    <link href="http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2013/10/27/Akka-DDD-CQRS-Event-Sourcing-And-Me/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-27T20:47:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2013/10/27/Akka-DDD-CQRS-Event-Sourcing-And-Me</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Introduction</h2>

<p>I’ve been involved in some really interesting discussions on the Akka User mailing list of late and thought it would be good to translate something I wrote, in one particular thread, into a blog post.</p>

<p>I recently became rather obsessed with Domain Driven Design (DDD), CQRS and Event Sourcing. Given an existing passion for Akka (actor based programming), it dawned on me that the actor model might be an extremely good fit for the aforementioned “Holy Trio” of paradigms/patterns. Whilst trying to build a prototype, I brought up the topic on the Akka User mailing list and became aware that the Akka Team were actively working on Akka Persistence, which is well ahead of my dirty little prototype! For one reason or another, within a post on the mailing list, I ended up brain dumping my understanding of how Akka Persistence and the “Holy Trio” fits together, so here follows a blog friendly version!</p>

<h2>Akka and the Holy Trio</h2>

<p>So, it seems like the actor model fits very well with DDD, and I&rsquo;m not the first person to think this &ndash; <a href="https://vaughnvernon.co/">Vaughn Vernon</a> is well ahead of the game!</p>

<p>It feels quite natural to me to consider an actor analogous to an aggregate root (in DDD speak). Rather than just seeing an actor as a mediator sitting in front of a database, you see the actor conceptually as an entity. By incorporating event sourcing, the actor works on the basis of processing a command (representing some action) and outputting one or many events that represent the result of processing that command. At all times the actor encapsulates its current state, which can simply be seen as the result of a series of ordered events applied to it.</p>

<p>Initially, it’s actually quite helpful to ignore persistence requirements altogether and just rely on the state within the actor – in this way you don’t allow persistence concerns to influence the way you design your domain – I often find that domain models end up messy because, despite attempts to avoid doing so, persistence concerns end up, in one form or another, leaking into the business logic. Any approach to building a domain layer, that can genuinely remove the need to consider persistence technologies, is an attractive proposition in my mind!</p>

<p>By following an event sourcing approach, persistence becomes no more complex than just persisting the events – that the actor produces – in an event store (journal). Given that events represent an immutable history of state changes, the journal can be append only, and that’s pretty exciting from a performance perspective. This is something that can quite clearly be bolted on once you’ve already put together a working in-memory only version of your domain – the actors themselves can be completely agnostic to the existence of the persistence mechanism. This is where Akka Persistence comes in – it works on the following basis:</p>

<ol>
<li>Actor receives command</li>
<li>Actor processes command (applies business logic) and produces events that represent results of processing</li>
<li>Events are persisted to journal</li>
<li>Events are applied to actor so it can update it&rsquo;s internal state</li>
</ol>


<p>Akka Persistence pretty much deals with everything other than the command handling step, which represents your custom business logic – Akka is not quite good enough (yet) to do that bit ;–)</p>

<p>Step 4 is quite important – it’s key that internal state is only applied once you’re sure events have been persisted to the journal. Also, by separating this step, it serves the additional purpose of allowing events in the journal to be replayed onto a “green” instance of the actor such to bring its internal state back up to current. Akka Persistence also has support for “snapshots” which allow you to take periodic snapshots of current state to be used as a performance optimisation when replaying events.</p>

<p>So, to sum up, the actor model just fits with the “Holy Trio”. It seems to deal with a majority of the pain points experienced when building a domain layer using more traditional CRUD techniques. It’s pretty exciting to me how natural this design feels without any need to consider using an ORM ;–)</p>

<h2>The Future</h2>

<p>And that’s the end of the blog friendly version of my brain dump! I truly believe the combination of the actor model with DDD, CQRS and Event Sourcing is going to become a very prevalent domain model design solution in the future.</p>

<p>I have to add that the Akka Team (including Patrik, Martin, Roland etc.) continue to be such an inspiration. Keep up the good work, guys!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Access logs in Play! using RequestHeader tags]]></title>
    <link href="http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2013/07/14/access-logs-in-play-using-requestheader-tags/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-14T13:30:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2013/07/14/access-logs-in-play-using-requestheader-tags</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Log files as event streams</h2>

<p>Having long been a fan of treating <a href="http://12factor.net/logs">log files as streams of events</a> (JSON formatted), I thought it would be useful to share a little bit of code to demonstrate how to achieve access style logging in a Play application. There&rsquo;s certainly more than one solution to this problem (there is, for example, a nice little plugin here: <a href="https://github.com/briannesbitt/play-accesslog">https://github.com/briannesbitt/play-accesslog</a>), but I wanted to share a little snippet of code &ndash; I&rsquo;ve used plenty of times in my own applications &ndash; utilising the RequestHeader tags feature in Play!.</p>

<p>Just after starting this post, I noticed another great <a href="http://matthiasnehlsen.com/blog/2013/07/09/transforming-logs-into-information/">article</a> from <a href="https://twitter.com/matthiasnehlsen">@matthiasnehlsen</a> about using <a href="http://kibana.org/">Kibana</a> to store log events generated in Play applications. Kibana is a great tool &ndash; backed by the awesome Elasticsearch &ndash; and I also highly recommend it. I won&rsquo;t go into any detail in this article about sending logs to Kibana as Matthias has done a great job of doing that :&ndash;) Suffice to say, though, the information in my article here would certainly play nicely with Kibana &ndash; I simply want to make you aware of how you can extract some useful information from Play to enhance your log events no matter where you might wish to send them (log files included!).</p>

<h2>RequestHeader tags</h2>

<p>So&hellip;back to this feature &ndash; <code>RequestHeader</code> tags! It turns out that Play associates some very useful &lsquo;tags&rsquo; along with the <code>RequestHeader</code> generated for each request. You can get hold of this <code>Map</code> of tags by calling <code>RequestHeader.tags</code>.</p>

<p>Given this learning, we can build a Play <code>EssentialFilter</code> &ndash; that will wrap every request &ndash; and log the JSON formatted request information to the Play <code>Logger</code>.</p>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
<span class='line-number'>20</span>
<span class='line-number'>21</span>
<span class='line-number'>22</span>
<span class='line-number'>23</span>
<span class='line-number'>24</span>
<span class='line-number'>25</span>
<span class='line-number'>26</span>
<span class='line-number'>27</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='scala'><span class='line'><span class="k">object</span> <span class="nc">AccessLogFilter</span> <span class="k">extends</span> <span class="nc">EssentialFilter</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">val</span> <span class="n">dateTimeFormat</span> <span class="k">=</span> <span class="nc">ISODateTimeFormat</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">ordinalDateTimeNoMillis</span><span class="o">()</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="k">def</span> <span class="n">apply</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">next</span><span class="k">:</span> <span class="kt">EssentialAction</span><span class="o">)</span> <span class="k">=</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="nc">EssentialAction</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="k">def</span> <span class="n">apply</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">rh</span><span class="k">:</span> <span class="kt">RequestHeader</span><span class="o">)</span> <span class="k">=</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="k">val</span> <span class="n">startTime</span> <span class="k">=</span> <span class="nc">System</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">currentTimeMillis</span><span class="o">()</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="k">def</span> <span class="n">logTime</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">result</span><span class="k">:</span> <span class="kt">PlainResult</span><span class="o">)</span><span class="k">:</span> <span class="kt">Result</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="k">val</span> <span class="n">event</span> <span class="k">=</span> <span class="nc">Json</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">obj</span><span class="o">(</span>
</span><span class='line'>          <span class="s">&quot;uri&quot;</span> <span class="o">-&gt;</span> <span class="n">rh</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">uri</span><span class="o">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>          <span class="s">&quot;timestamp&quot;</span> <span class="o">-&gt;</span> <span class="n">dateTimeFormat</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">print</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="k">new</span> <span class="nc">DateTime</span><span class="o">),</span>
</span><span class='line'>          <span class="s">&quot;execution_time&quot;</span> <span class="o">-&gt;</span> <span class="o">(</span><span class="nc">System</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">currentTimeMillis</span><span class="o">()</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="n">startTime</span><span class="o">),</span>
</span><span class='line'>          <span class="s">&quot;status&quot;</span> <span class="o">-&gt;</span> <span class="n">result</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">header</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">status</span><span class="o">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>          <span class="s">&quot;tags&quot;</span> <span class="o">-&gt;</span> <span class="nc">Json</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">toJson</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">rh</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">tags</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">map</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">entry</span> <span class="k">=&gt;</span> <span class="n">entry</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">_1</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">toLowerCase</span> <span class="o">-&gt;</span> <span class="n">entry</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">_2</span><span class="o">))</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="o">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="nc">Logger</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">info</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="nc">Json</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">stringify</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">event</span><span class="o">))</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="n">result</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="o">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="n">next</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">rh</span><span class="o">).</span><span class="n">map</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="k">case</span> <span class="n">plain</span><span class="k">:</span> <span class="kt">PlainResult</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="n">logTime</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">plain</span><span class="o">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="k">case</span> <span class="n">async</span><span class="k">:</span> <span class="kt">AsyncResult</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="n">async</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">transform</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">logTime</span><span class="o">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="o">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="o">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>  <span class="o">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>On top of adding the tags (and some other available request info) to the JSON object, you&rsquo;ll see the execution time is also captured alongside. To enable this filter, we simply create a custom <code>Global.scala</code>, in the default package:</p>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='scala'><span class='line'><span class="k">object</span> <span class="nc">Global</span> <span class="k">extends</span> <span class="nc">WithFilters</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="nc">AccessLogFilter</span><span class="o">)</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Here is an example log line generated by this filter (prettified for readability):</p>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='json'><span class='line'><span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="nt">&quot;uri&quot;</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="s2">&quot;/search/*&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="nt">&quot;timestamp&quot;</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="s2">&quot;2013-194T18:14:27+01:00&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="nt">&quot;execution_time&quot;</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="mi">20</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="nt">&quot;status&quot;</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="mi">200</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="nt">&quot;tags&quot;</span><span class="p">:{</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nt">&quot;route_verb&quot;</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="s2">&quot;GET&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nt">&quot;route_action_method&quot;</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="s2">&quot;search&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nt">&quot;route_pattern&quot;</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="s2">&quot;/search/$searchString&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nt">&quot;route_controller&quot;</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="s2">&quot;controllers.Application&quot;</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>      <span class="nt">&quot;route_comments&quot;</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="s2">&quot;Root action&quot;</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>One of the most useful things about capturing the tags is that you get easy access to &lsquo;normalized&rsquo; actions/endpoints. So, it&rsquo;s immediately easy (e.g. in a tool like Kibana) to pick all log events related to a specific action. The URI alone is not good enough because parameterized path variables, or query string parameters, lead to non-unique URI representations for the same logical action bindings.</p>

<p>As the filter wraps every request, you will see log lines generated for static assets too &ndash; something that is most likely too verbose for most use cases. It&rsquo;s not too hard to apply filtering to the URI extension to ignore assets, but I left it out of the example code for the sake of cleanliness.</p>

<p>Keep on logging!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reactive, real-time log search with Play, Akka, AngularJS and Elasticsearch]]></title>
    <link href="http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2013/07/08/reactive-real-time-log-search-with-play-akka-angularjs-and-elasticsearch/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-08T12:25:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2013/07/08/reactive-real-time-log-search-with-play-akka-angularjs-and-elasticsearch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Introduction</h2>

<p>So, I&rsquo;ve decided to contribute an Activator Template to TypeSafe (will submit soon, promise!). Having recently become more and more involved in Elasticsearch, I saw a great opportunity to put together a neat &ldquo;reactive&rdquo; application combining Play &amp; Akka with the &ldquo;bonsai cool&#8221; <a href="http://www.elasticsearch.org/guide/reference/api/percolate/">percolation</a> feature of Elasticsearch. Then, to put a cherry on top, use AngularJS on the client-side to create a dynamically updating UI.</p>

<p>What I came up with is slightly contrived &ndash; a very basic real-time log entry search tool &ndash; but I think it provides a really nice base for apps that want to integrate this bunch of technologies.</p>

<p><a href="http://DrewEaster.github.io/images/real-time-search.png"><img class="center" src="http://DrewEaster.github.io/images/real-time-search.png" width="600" height="264"></a></p>

<p>All the code for the application is available on Github <a href="https://github.com/drewzilla/realtime-search">here</a>. In this post, I&rsquo;ve attempted to dissect the Activator Template tutorial I&rsquo;ve written and regurgitate it in blog form.</p>

<h3>Play and Akka</h3>

<p>Play and Akka are used to implement the reactive server-side application. The application favours SSE (Server Sent Events) to push updates to the client. The template introduces a number of interesting topics, including Play Iteratees/Enumerators and Akka Actors.</p>

<h3>AngularJS</h3>

<p>AngularJS has been chosen on the client-side to demonstrate how simple it can be to build a dynamic, single page user experience with very little code.</p>

<h3>Elasticsearch</h3>

<p>The &ldquo;bonsai cool&rdquo; percolation feature of Elasticsearch achieves the real-time search aspect of the application. The application starts up an embedded Elasticsearch node, so no need to run your own external instance. Take a look at <a href="https://github.com/drewzilla/realtime-search/blob/master/app/utils/EmbeddedESServer.scala">EmbeddedESServer</a> for the embedded server code. There is a custom <a href="https://github.com/drewzilla/realtime-search/blob/master/app/Global.scala">Global</a> where the embedded server is started and shutdown as part of the application lifecycle.</p>

<h2>The Actors</h2>

<p>The application has three actors:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/drewzilla/realtime-search/blob/master/app/actors/MainSearchActor.scala">MainSearchActor</a> supervises and coordinates data flows</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/drewzilla/realtime-search/blob/master/app/actors/ElasticSearchActor.scala">ElasticsearchActor</a> interacts with Elasticsearch percolation API</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/drewzilla/realtime-search/blob/master/app/actors/LogEntryProducerActor.scala">LogEntryProducerActor</a> generates &lsquo;random&rsquo; log entry data</li>
</ul>


<h3>MainSearchActor</h3>

<p>This actor&rsquo;s job is to coordinate the reactive parts of the application and supervise the other actors. It is the main dependency of the application&rsquo;s single Play <a href="https://github.com/drewzilla/realtime-search/blob/master/app/controllers/Application.scala">controller</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Starting/stopping a search</strong></p>

<p>The actor responds to a <code>StartSearch</code> message by &lsquo;replying&rsquo; with an <code>Enumerator</code> to the sender. The <code>Enumerator</code> wraps a unicast channel to which log entries are pushed that match the query string sent within the message. Let&rsquo;s take a look at some code:</p>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='scala'><span class='line'><span class="k">private</span> <span class="k">def</span> <span class="n">startSearching</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">startSearch</span><span class="k">:</span> <span class="kt">StartSearch</span><span class="o">)</span> <span class="k">=</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nc">Concurrent</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">unicast</span><span class="o">[</span><span class="kt">JsValue</span><span class="o">](</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="n">onStart</span> <span class="k">=</span> <span class="o">(</span><span class="n">c</span><span class="o">)</span> <span class="k">=&gt;</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="n">channels</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="o">(</span><span class="n">startSearch</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">id</span> <span class="o">-&gt;</span> <span class="n">c</span><span class="o">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="n">elasticSearchActor</span> <span class="o">!</span> <span class="n">startSearch</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="o">},</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="n">onComplete</span> <span class="k">=</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="n">self</span> <span class="o">!</span> <span class="nc">StopSearch</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">startSearch</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">id</span><span class="o">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="o">},</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="n">onError</span> <span class="k">=</span> <span class="o">(</span><span class="n">str</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="n">in</span><span class="o">)</span> <span class="k">=&gt;</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="n">self</span> <span class="o">!</span> <span class="nc">StopSearch</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">startSearch</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">id</span><span class="o">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="o">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="o">).</span><span class="n">onDoneEnumerating</span><span class="o">(</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="n">callback</span> <span class="k">=</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="n">self</span> <span class="o">!</span> <span class="nc">StopSearch</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">startSearch</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">id</span><span class="o">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="o">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="o">)</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The Play Iteratees library has the very handy <code>Concurrent</code> utilities. In this case, <code>Concurrent.unicast</code> is called to create an <code>Enumerator</code> that encloses a <code>Concurrent.Channel</code>. When the channel starts (<code>onStart</code>), it is stored in a map local to the actor (using UUID as key) and the <code>StartSearch</code> message is forwarded onto the <code>ElasticSearchActor</code> where the query will be percolated in Elasticsearch. It&rsquo;s worth noting that this code is not production ready &ndash; it ought to be a transactional operation, i.e. we should only store the channel once we know Elasticsearch has successfully percolated the query. You will notice that a <code>StopSearch</code> message is sent to <code>self</code> such that the channel is removed from the local map, and the percolated query is deleted, when the channel is no longer useful (i.e. is closed by the client, or an error occurs).</p>

<p><strong>Broadcasting matching results</strong></p>

<p>The actor will receive a <code>SearchMatch</code> message when a log entry has matched a percolated query.</p>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='scala'><span class='line'><span class="k">private</span> <span class="k">def</span> <span class="n">broadcastMatch</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">searchMatch</span><span class="k">:</span> <span class="kt">SearchMatch</span><span class="o">)</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="n">searchMatch</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">matchingChannelIds</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">foreach</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="n">channels</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">get</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="k">_</span><span class="o">).</span><span class="n">map</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="k">_</span> <span class="n">push</span> <span class="n">searchMatch</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">logEntry</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">data</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="o">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="o">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>On receipt of the message, each matching id is iterated over and the corresponding channel is retrieved from the local map. The log entry is then pushed to the channel, and thus onto the client.</p>

<p><strong>Scheduling log entry creation</strong></p>

<p>The actor uses the Akka scheduler to send a <code>Tick</code> to the <code>LogEntryProducerActor</code> every second &ndash; in the real world, this would obviously be unnecessary, as genuine log entries would be fed into the application in some other way. The <code>Tick</code> is sent to <code>self</code> before being forwarded on to the <code>LogEntryProducerActor</code>.</p>

<h3>ElasticsearchActor</h3>

<p>This actor has responsibility for both registering queries in Elasticsearch and percolating log entry documents against those queries. Rather than utilise the Elasticsearch Java Client, the code, instead, crafts the Elasticsearch API calls manually, demonstrating the use of the asynchronous Play WS API to execute them. For simplicity, the calls are hard coded to talk to Elasticsearch on localhost:9200 (where the embedded server will be listening).</p>

<p>The code is fairly self explanatory within this actor. Do note that there is a lack of error handling on the API calls thus making this actor unsuitable for production use in its current form. It is recommended you read the Elasticsearch <a href="http://www.elasticsearch.org/guide/reference/api/percolate/">documentation on percolation</a> to learn more about this powerful feature.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s one little important gotcha this code has avoided &ndash; closing over the <code>sender</code> ref in an asynchronous callback block. The <code>sender</code> ref is part of the shared mutable state of the actor and so, if the actor were to reply to the sender in the percolate callback, a race condition would be encountered if another thread had modified the actor&rsquo;s state before the percolation call to Elasticsearch had completed. This race condition has been avoided by ensuring to &lsquo;freeze&rsquo; the <code>sender</code> ref, by sending it to a private function:</p>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='scala'><span class='line'><span class="k">private</span> <span class="k">def</span> <span class="n">percolate</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">logJson</span><span class="k">:</span> <span class="kt">JsValue</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="n">requestor</span><span class="k">:</span> <span class="kt">ActorRef</span><span class="o">)</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>and close over the parameter instead.</p>

<h3>LogEntryProducerActor</h3>

<p>I won&rsquo;t go into the detail of this actor. Suffice to say, its job is to generate a random, JSON formatted log event whenever it receives a <code>Tick</code> message. In reality, a genuine source of log events would replace this actor.</p>

<h2>The Play Controller</h2>

<p>As most of the server-side logic exists within the actors, the single Play controller is very simple. The most interesting aspect of the controller is the action that opens an event stream connected with the client:</p>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='scala'><span class='line'><span class="k">def</span> <span class="n">search</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">searchString</span><span class="k">:</span> <span class="kt">String</span><span class="o">)</span> <span class="k">=</span> <span class="nc">Action</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nc">Async</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="o">(</span><span class="n">searchActor</span> <span class="o">?</span> <span class="nc">StartSearch</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">searchString</span> <span class="k">=</span> <span class="n">searchString</span><span class="o">)).</span><span class="n">map</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>            <span class="k">case</span> <span class="nc">SearchFeed</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">out</span><span class="o">)</span> <span class="k">=&gt;</span> <span class="nc">Ok</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">stream</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="n">out</span> <span class="o">&amp;&gt;</span> <span class="nc">EventSource</span><span class="o">()).</span><span class="n">as</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="s">&quot;text/event-stream&quot;</span><span class="o">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>        <span class="o">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="o">}</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The most important thing to note is the use of the Akka &lsquo;ask&rsquo; pattern of message exchange (notice the use of &lsquo;?&rsquo; instead of &lsquo;!&rsquo;). This differs from the more typical fire-and-forget approach in that we&rsquo;re able to asynchronously pick up a reply from the recipient actor. In this scenario, a <code>StartSearch</code> message is sent to the <code>MainSearchActor</code> which replies with an <code>Enumerator</code> used to stream search results to the client. Given the use of the &lsquo;ask&rsquo; pattern, we wrap the action logic in an <code>Async</code> block &ndash; so not to hold up other requests &ndash; rather than blocking until the <code>Future</code> yields a result.</p>

<h2>The User Interface</h2>

<p>The key parts of the application UI are:</p>

<ol>
<li>A Play <a href="https://github.com/drewzilla/realtime-search/blob/master/app/views/index.scala.html">template</a> with AngularJS specific markup</li>
<li>A single AngularJS <a href="https://github.com/drewzilla/realtime-search/blob/master/app/assets/javascripts/controllers.js">controller</a></li>
</ol>


<p>The application makes use of the <a href="http://www.webjars.org/">WebJars</a> project to simplify the introduction of its JS and CSS dependencies (e.g. AngularJS and Twitter Bootstrap).</p>

<h3>UI Template</h3>

<p>Firstly, the opening <code>&lt;div&gt;</code> is linked to the controller <code>SearchCtrl</code> that subsequently enables the automagical databinding power of AngularJS. A simple search form captures an Apache Lucene formatted query string. A search can be started by clicking on the &lsquo;Search&rsquo; button which invokes the <code>startSearching()</code> function defined in the controller. Finally, you can see the use of AngularJS two-way databinding to render matching search results contained within the view model (only displays the latest 10 matches):</p>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='scala'><span class='line'><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">tr</span> <span class="n">ng</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="n">repeat</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s">&quot;searchResult in searchResults | limitTo:10&quot;</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h3>The AngularJS Controller</h3>

<p>The AngularJS controller is fairly straightforward. The key part is handling a new search:</p>

<figure class='code'> <div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='scala'><span class='line'><span class="nc">$scope</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">startSearching</span> <span class="k">=</span> <span class="n">function</span> <span class="o">()</span> <span class="o">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nc">$scope</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">stopSearching</span><span class="o">()</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nc">$scope</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">searchResults</span> <span class="k">=</span> <span class="o">[];</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nc">$scope</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">searchFeed</span> <span class="k">=</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="nc">EventSource</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="s">&quot;/search/&quot;</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="nc">$scope</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">searchString</span><span class="o">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>    <span class="nc">$scope</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">searchFeed</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">addEventListener</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="s">&quot;message&quot;</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="nc">$scope</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">addSearchResult</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="kc">false</span><span class="o">);</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">};</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Firstly, an existing search is stopped (if running) and the results model cleared (will automagically clear any existing results from the HTML markup). Secondly, an event stream connection is made to the server and an event listener is added that pushes matching search results into the model as they arrive from the server.</p>

<p>As we are updating the model (in the <code>addSearchResult</code> function) outside of it&rsquo;s knowledge, we&rsquo;ve had to explicitly tell Angular that we&rsquo;ve pushed a new result to the model by wrapping the code in a function passed to <code>$scope.apply</code>. See the Angular docs for the <a href="http://docs.angularjs.org/api/ng.$rootScope.Scope">$scope</a> object for more information.</p>

<h2>Using the application</h2>

<p>Fire up the application using <code>play run</code> and point your browser (not IE &ndash; it doesn&rsquo;t support SSE. Doh!) to <a href="http://localhost:9000">http://localhost:9000</a>. Using the application is as simple as entering an Apache Lucene formatted query. Please read the Lucene <a href="http://lucene.apache.org/core/4_3_1/queryparser/org/apache/lucene/queryparser/classic/package-summary.html#package_description">query parser syntax documentation</a> for more information on how to construct Lucene query strings. A simple example would be to enter &ldquo;GET&rdquo; as your query string, thus matching all log entries for GET requests.</p>

<p>Enjoy!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Taking a walk on the wild side]]></title>
    <link href="http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2013/03/16/taking-a-walk-on-the-wild-side/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-16T12:08:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2013/03/16/taking-a-walk-on-the-wild-side</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Having spent nearly 10 years doing my best to avoid wrestling with the client-side web, the necessity to better prepare myself for a new future (think tech startup) means I&rsquo;ve begun some serious dabbling on &ldquo;the wild side&rdquo;.</p>

<p>At first it was just a case of some casual flirting, but that has now extended as far as a proper first date.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve long been coming round to the idea that, in order to build a rich application experience in the browser, Java does not have the answer &ndash; for me, the Java component based framework experiments have failed (ThoughtWorks agreed with me in <a href="http://thoughtworks.fileburst.com/assets/technology-radar-october-2012.pdf">October 2012</a>). I feel sad to say this because, whilst I despised JSF right from the start, I kinda liked Wicket and Tapestry. Without wanting to get too heretical, the Java Swing programming model is grounded in some pretty solid coding patterns and, as close as Wicket comes to realising a similar approach on the web, you just can&rsquo;t get away from the fact that the web just ain&rsquo;t really built for that stuff.</p>

<p>So, that date I was referring to was with a cute little beast called <a href="http://angularjs.org/">AngularJS</a>. After initially being slightly sick in my mouth at the thought of a journey beyond statically typed languages, I&rsquo;ve begun to come round to the idea that JavaScript needn&rsquo;t be so bad as long as you play by the <a href="http://www.amazon.co.uk/JavaScript-Good-Parts-Douglas-Crockford/dp/0596517742">rules</a>, and you couple your exploration with a neat framework like AngularJS. With AngularJS, I&rsquo;m once again playing with a component-ish framework that is not trying to exist on top of an unsuitable protocol &ndash; the rich interactions live in the browser where they feel most at home.</p>

<p>One of the coolest things about AngularJS is that I can even apply some of my most loyal of server-side patterns (I&rsquo;m thinking dependency injection) when hacking client code. And, even more importantly, I still get my server-side fix through building predictable, testable, stateless APIs for the stateful client to consume.</p>

<p>I definitely see this going to a second date, and beyond.</p>

<p>On a final note, I do feel that <a href="http://twitter.github.com/bootstrap/">Twitter Bootstrap</a> deserves a special mention here as well. There&rsquo;s no doubt that I suck at CSS, and I truly mean that. But, with Bootstrap, no longer must server-side developers walk naked and exposed in the presentational side of the web. I don&rsquo;t care for CSS &ndash; I don&rsquo;t think I ever will &ndash; but with Bootstrap I&rsquo;ve now got half a chance of making web apps that don&rsquo;t only work good, but look good at the same time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Play2 &amp; Scala – A new beginning]]></title>
    <link href="http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2012/10/14/play2-and-scala-a-new-beginning/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-14T11:49:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://DrewEaster.github.io/blog/2012/10/14/play2-and-scala-a-new-beginning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today marks the beginning of a new chapter in my software engineering life. I’ve been an enterprise Java dev for so many years that it’s boring to even talk about it. Don’ t get me wrong, I love my job (if you can even call it a job) but sometimes one needs a spark, a chance to re-experience a honeymoon period that extends beyond love and into a kind of uncontrollable, rapturous madness.</p>

<p>The murmurings for this new chapter began a few weeks ago when I enrolled on Martin Odersky’s “Functional Programming Principles in Scala” course – a fantastic FREE online course that runs for seven weeks, supported by <a href="http://www.epfl.ch/">EPFL</a> in Switzerland. For sure, I’ve been well aware of the rise of Scala within the industry but had never gotten round to really indulging in this exciting language (except, maybe, for getting through a few chapters of <a href="http://www.artima.com/shop/programming_in_scala_2ed/">Programming in Scala</a> on my Kindle). The same goes for the <a href="http://www.playframework.org/">Play! Framework</a>, something I’ve kept an eye on at arm’s length for quite a few years now.</p>

<p>I’m now into the fourth week of Odersky’s course and, following completion of the first three challenging, but almost perversely absorbing, assignments, today I decided it was time to fire up my first Play2 application. Fortunately, I picked up a little freelance client project last week and it was a bit of a no brainer, given my newly mobilised appetite for all things Scala, to implement it using a technology (Play!) I really knew was overdue an evaluation.</p>

<p>Just a few hours after downloading Play! 2.0.4, I have fallen hopelessly under it’s spell – I’ve been wandering around the house in what resembles a drunken stupor, close to screaming with excitement at what I’ve learned and been able to achieve in just one afternoon. My face aches, my jaw having been locked into a permanent smile. I know this is the future, though I feel a certain degree of sadness as I acknowledge my love affair with JEE, and it’s wonderful layer upon layer of abstraction, to be very nearly over (we need to stay friends, mind – my day job will see to that).</p>

<p>The anticipation. The butterflies. So the journey begins.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
